<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-09T22:10:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alexander Ladd</title><subtitle>An amazing website.</subtitle><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Not Even Wrong</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/Not_Even_Wrong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Even Wrong" /><published>2021-12-06T13:16:13-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T13:16:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/Not_Even_Wrong</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/Not_Even_Wrong/">&lt;p&gt;Wow, I just found out what it means to be “Not even wrong”. The phase, coined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Pauli&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Pauli&lt;/a&gt; has just given me a huge slice of humble pie. Basically not even wrong is used to describe a totally failed conjecture. If something is meaningless, it’s definitely not right, but it’s not wrong either since you have to be coherent and pointed to be wrong. This has changed the way I think about wrong and right in science. Sometimes, as all scientists do, I use big words when I’m not exactly sure what I’m talking about to make it seem like I do. And the truth is, there’s no cookie and no medal for being hard to understand. From now on, if I’m unsure but I stil want to conjecture, I am going to do it with as basic of an explnation as possible. This way, if I’m misguided I’ll get caught fast instead of getting by on jibberish. This is the route to actually being right about a lot of things one day. Well, I hope that day comes, for now I’d rather be wrong than not even wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/doing_it_wrong.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;you're doing it wrong!&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="posts" /><summary type="html">Wow, I just found out what it means to be “Not even wrong”. The phase, coined by Wolfgang Pauli has just given me a huge slice of humble pie. Basically not even wrong is used to describe a totally failed conjecture. If something is meaningless, it’s definitely not right, but it’s not wrong either since you have to be coherent and pointed to be wrong. This has changed the way I think about wrong and right in science. Sometimes, as all scientists do, I use big words when I’m not exactly sure what I’m talking about to make it seem like I do. And the truth is, there’s no cookie and no medal for being hard to understand. From now on, if I’m unsure but I stil want to conjecture, I am going to do it with as basic of an explnation as possible. This way, if I’m misguided I’ll get caught fast instead of getting by on jibberish. This is the route to actually being right about a lot of things one day. Well, I hope that day comes, for now I’d rather be wrong than not even wrong.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 3" /><published>2021-11-18T13:16:13-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-18T13:16:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review3/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0959438821000593&quot;&gt;From synapse to network: models of information storage and retrieval in neural circuits
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://aljadeff.ucsd.edu/&quot;&gt;Johnatan (Yonatan) Aljadeff&lt;/a&gt; et al.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Citation: Aljadeff, Johnatan, et al. “From synapse to network: models of information storage and retrieval in neural circuits.” Current opinion in neurobiology 70 (2021): 24-33.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intro
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Stimuli dependent patterns in neural circuity lead to research in mechanisms for synaptic updates and and how such modifications change network dynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Introduces two theoretical approachs to modeling dynamics of delay periods in updates – biophysical connecitivity matrix and supervised learning approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This paper is gonna look at the former.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Synaptic Plasticity rules
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Some STDP curves seem useful &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; butthe calcium dynamics &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; seem to alter these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In inferring directly from &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; theres a limitation in measuring both pre and post synaptic acitivty.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;I’m curious how this limitaiton works. Is it a resolution thing, or is the issue that it’s hard to dissociate between pre and post synaptic updates?&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Lim et al. study seems to be leading as far as infering in vitro pre synaptic rules.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;So far ML models are being developed but only shown success on synthetic data.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;plasticity can be induced by pairing presynaptic spikes with postsynaptic plateu potentials over longer timecales.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Network dynamics
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What type of network dynamics emerger from networks with these learning rules? Two types of scenarios, one where learning and retireval happen in seperate phases and another where the happen concurrently.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Netowrks with learning seperate from retrieval
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;These networks demonstrate (converge?) to attractor states&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;A lot of recurrent activity represents higher chatoic acitivity and less like to converge to solid representations but this is similar to the affect of delayed reponses tasks, where dynamics are confined to a stable subspace but are chaotic within that constraint.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Q about figure 2: what do the colorful triangles mean here? I see the caption and that they are activited based on some corresponding output. But I wonder in the larger context here. Are these considered attractor states by definition? Or are there some caveats. Is there are strict defnition that can define these sets, or they just seem to be active corresponding to some external input, given some plasticity rule?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;AH, question is answered here – seems theres a paper on this and that they can be dubbed “hebbian assemblies” – cool.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Gotta love when all I have to do to have a question answered is keep reading. :blush:&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Networks with dynamic connectivity
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;needs additional stabilization betsides hebbian synaptic plasticity.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Here’s where E/I balance and recurrent connections come in.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Figure 3 panel I is really cool, there really seems to be some kind of normal pattern behind the overlap when different ensembles are activated. (I think I am understandign this figure correctly)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;One thing I wonder about the figure is what happens when several stimuli are presented in a sequence. What happens to fraction of overlap in network state then? How often do these small activated ensembles overlap?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Also I liked the column showing the subspaces.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Storage Capcacity
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ah, seems to go nicely with the previous questiona about encoding multiple stimuli in the network.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Do biological netowrks reach optimal storage capcity as given by information encoding optimality gurantees on state space of connectivity matrix?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Answer to this question depends on the constraints of state space for optimality gurantee – general unsuprivied = open question, hebbian unsupervied = networks seem to use this capcity.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Likely we are more in the second case given other factors that encode info (like E/I ratio)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; Garder bound seems important for this, I should learn about it.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Wow, seems that optimizing for information storage can recreate non trivial aspects of synaptic connectivity. Several studies cited here, could be interesting further reading since these properties seem new to me (except E/I balance).&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Discussion
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; Ref 33 seems really interesting as challenge to persistent activity hypothesis.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Temporal statistics here seem to be a real sticking point, hebbian networks can be persistent or sequential (what is squential btw) based on the statistics of the input during learning.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;This isn’t what I thought the autor meant by temporal statisics. I thought they would be a post hoc test, not a pre (or input related) thing. Here is a gap in my knowledge. &lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; ref 49 might be an intersting follow up.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Approach outlined here: biophysical synaptic updates can be contasted with supervised learning apporaches for different pros and cons.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Con for supervised learning is that some plasticity rules do satisfy locality constraints and are not biologicallly possible.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;integration of unsupervised and reward based into this approach will be good future work.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Can progress in experimental (reponse tasks) or computational (advancing biologically plausbile update rules in models) directions.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">From synapse to network: models of information storage and retrieval in neural circuits by Johnatan (Yonatan) Aljadeff et al.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 4</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 4" /><published>2021-11-18T13:16:13-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-18T13:16:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review4/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talyarkoni.org/blog/2018/08/18/if-we-already-understood-the-brain-would-we-even-know-it/&quot;&gt;If we already understood the brain, would we even know it?&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://talyarkoni.org/&quot;&gt;Tal Yarkoni&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Citation: Yarkoni, Tal. “If We Already Understood the Brain, Would We Even Know It?” Tal Yarkoni Blog, 29 Aug. 2019, https://www.talyarkoni.org/blog/2018/08/18/if-we-already-understood-the-brain-would-we-even-know-it/.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First, I like this article already. If I had a dollar for everytime I hear a neuroscientist bemoan “we know nothing about the brain”…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The assesment that we know ~ .1 % of the things there are to know about neuroscience is an interesting one for sure. Also that in 200 years or so we can shut down neuroscience.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This is a reason I am so happy I reviewed a blog instead of a paper today. Finally, we can speculate for arugments sake. Makes reading way more interesting then having to use axioms, posulates and citations for every claim made.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The dissonance in the relationship between our personal understanding of the field and the cumulative knowledge in the field is really a bit concerning. I think this is pointing out that the emperor has no clothes.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In order to build the skills to be an excellent experimental scientist one must spend a lot of time working hands on in a lab.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;On the other hand, to understand the field they must spend so much time reading.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;There’s a tension here that like Tal says, causes us to ask the same question in different ways quite often.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oooh, it is a tough question to wonder “why does such and such network to activate?”
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;We can sometimes answer things like &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; etc. but why is difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This is on the DMN example.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As I understand the general intelligence part of this blog the message is this: g_f, or general intelligence, is an effect with a slew of correlated causes (mechanisms involving attention, abstraciton etc.) and to try and pick out &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; cause of intellgence is a losing propostion. general intelligence emerges among many influencing factors.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This seems like a microcosm of the problem. We are looking for short answers to long quetions. If we want to “fully understand” how a mechanism or circuit works, it’ll invovle synthesizing complicated information at scales from mico to macro.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This reminds me of integrative biology class tests where I had to detail 5 or 10 steps in a response on autonomous nervous system. The nice part about this is we often looked at one level of complexity. We’d never be asked about the morphological changes to the neurons in the circuit becaue that’s just way too much information to have synthesized – it’s a big jump.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In this sense, the full answers to how circuitry in the brain work aren’t obligated to be nice and digestable – but our explanations are.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I like that Dan is always asking for a &lt;em&gt;core principle&lt;/em&gt; and D’Ann is always just denying the simplicity of one &lt;em&gt;core principle&lt;/em&gt; existing.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And we leave off the article basically on the same note.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sure we might be able to learn more and more detailed and expressive computational models and these models may even be able to account for all the variance we can hope for … but at this point we’d probably still be asking “what’s the underlying principle?”.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think this dilemma relates back to the Searle’s chinese room argument (Searle 2009), it’s like sure you can make make a latent space model that’s very expressive of the mechanism but this is all input/output … you haven’t truly learned the language.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I like to think that Tal would agree with me here: The computation &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the language. The implementation level story is all there is.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As we understand the computational story of the brain … it’s incredibly messy and convoluted.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What I mean is that latent models and manifolds are tricky to parameterize and design in a way where they can a) be accurate in predicting states and b) be human-understandable.
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Neil deGrasse Tyson. Aug 21, 2017&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;“The universe is under no obligation to make sense to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anyways, this blog seems to stand opposite of the aisle of a particular view in Jeff Hawkins’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Intelligence-Understanding-Creation-Intelligent-Machines/dp/0805078533/ref=asc_df_0805078533/?tag=hyprod-20&amp;amp;linkCode=df0&amp;amp;hvadid=312128454859&amp;amp;hvpos=&amp;amp;hvnetw=g&amp;amp;hvrand=2933067035242335183&amp;amp;hvpone=&amp;amp;hvptwo=&amp;amp;hvqmt=&amp;amp;hvdev=c&amp;amp;hvdvcmdl=&amp;amp;hvlocint=&amp;amp;hvlocphy=9031201&amp;amp;hvtargid=pla-432166617256&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;On Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The view is this:
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Paraphrased from Hawkins, J., &amp;amp; Blakeslee, S. (2004). On intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Imagine that aliens look at Earth and see a bunch of roads and they catalog every detail of each road and which one leads where etc. but they don’t really understand what the roads &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt;. That is until they understand that humans couldn’t teleport places and need roads to move from one place to another in cars. Once this detail falls into place, the functionality begins to make a lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Obviously this is in defense that there are some intuitve explanations that can be delivered through human understable theory.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As is often the case, I don’t think we’ll ever be able to ring a bell and declare one of these viewpoints the winner. In fact, I think that though they may stand on opposite sides of the aisle – to declare that they are at odds is even a stretch.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think a more appropriate understanding between the “there is a simple theory and once we know it, things will make more sense” and the “there’s no magic at the bottom that’ll simplify things for our tiny brains” is that these are just two different flavors of possible answers that can be served to the multitude of questions about the brain.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And one final note. I really appreciate the Tal’s perspective in this blog because it’s a lot harder to take than Jeff’s in the quote. There are just some questions that can’t be answered. For example, the question &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are some people taller than others is just ill posed. There are a variety of reasons, not one causal explanation we can point to everytime.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We’ll probably never stop asking well-posed and ill-posed questions about neuroscience. Or maybe we can just abandon our posts and leave it to philosophers. Either way, time to make peace with that now.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can choose to grimace as we stare into the void, or we can have a good laugh.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Citations
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hawkins, J., &amp;amp; Blakeslee, S. (2004). On intelligence. New York: Times Books.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Searle, John. “Chinese room argument.” Scholarpedia 4.8 (2009): 3100.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">If we already understood the brain, would we even know it? by Tal Yarkoni.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 1" /><published>2021-11-14T13:16:13-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-14T13:16:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review1/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review 1 : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eneuro.org/content/8/2/ENEURO.0131-21.2021&quot;&gt;In Silico&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://fairhalllab.com/&quot; title=&quot;Title&quot;&gt;Dr. Fairhall&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Citation: Fairhall, Adrienne L. “In silico: where next?.” &lt;em&gt;Eneuro&lt;/em&gt; 8.2 (2021).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intro
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This writing starts out by laying out the context of 2013, a very important year for funding large neuroscience research initiatives, the U.S. BRAIN projects and the European Human Brain Project (HBP).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Furthers discussion into brain atlases from Allen institute and recent developments in imaging and recording techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mentioned a paper I found interested on neural networks as simulation tools : &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28668365/&quot;&gt;Barak 2007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Key Question: “On this backdrop, what are valuable targets for future
large-scale spending?”
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;To me, this seems to be the transition from historical background to the discussion of what next.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;And here Dr. Fairhall points out a key issue facing large scale collaboration in brain science: What big experiments and datasets will lead to transformative research?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The answer being, there’s not really some resounding agreement.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Possible answers
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Dr. Abbot suggests the approach of a deatiled cellular model of a mouse brain, however, as HBP has experienced, there is a challenge here with integrating biophysical modeling with levels of connectivity (gap junction, neuromodulation, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;An alternative approach is discussed as a brain activity map that bridges existing theories about different regions of the brain in modeling one activity in order to align existsing theories.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;The challenge here seems to be design. How does one actually assemble all these odds and ends.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I thought this quote was interesting:
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;In Silico (Fairhall 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;“IARPA’s MICrONS program is […] a collaborative effort to reconstruct the connectome of a section of visual cortex whose activity has been characterized in vivo. By establishing the functional relevance of specific neurons, this project addresses some of the criticisms made of both the Blue Brain (Yong, 2019) and connectomics approaches.”&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting for a few reasons. First, I wonder what the actual criticms are in the cited paper, I hear about criticsms all the time but yet I don’t quite know what they are. Second, I wonder how this project manages to address such criticsms. An easy guess is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;function relevance&lt;/code&gt; suggests this project is doing more to link modeling with functionality … but this is still vague in my mind,&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Finally, mention of a collaborative study where different groups measure populations of 1000 neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now that the author has introduced the problem and several approaches. it’s time to conclude and leave the reader feeling warm and fuzzy that we will solve all the problems in neuroscience. Kidding of course.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Author notes that projects that produce a “product” such as Allen datasest are less risky than projects that aim to tackle large problems.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Suggests diversifying research investment across labs.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Then model of brain observatories gathering data on a large scale and then smaller labs performing analysis on these dataset.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;The nice part about this is that the datasets will be well vetted by various research groups.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;And computational neuroscientists can save some money on having to run large scale experiments – they get nice data.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;We know a lot but we know nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The last line here really hits home. There is a massive body of research on neuroscience, yet unifying theories (across levels of complexity) are few and far between.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overall, this is a great paper to introduce some of the key questions facing large collaborative neuroscience and was a really nice read for my first review. I can imagine I’ll be reading more papers with a lot of narrative gating, but this was not that. It was straight the point and clear. Sure some parts were not elaborated on, but the citations are there and I can follow the trail. I believe this is a balance one has to strike in order to deliver a clear message and something I hope to take with me in my own writing.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Good stuff :) thanks.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Review 1 : In Silico by Dr. Fairhall Citation: Fairhall, Adrienne L. “In silico: where next?.” Eneuro 8.2 (2021). Intro This writing starts out by laying out the context of 2013, a very important year for funding large neuroscience research initiatives, the U.S. BRAIN projects and the European Human Brain Project (HBP). Furthers discussion into brain atlases from Allen institute and recent developments in imaging and recording techniques. Mentioned a paper I found interested on neural networks as simulation tools : Barak 2007 Key Question: “On this backdrop, what are valuable targets for future large-scale spending?” To me, this seems to be the transition from historical background to the discussion of what next. And here Dr. Fairhall points out a key issue facing large scale collaboration in brain science: What big experiments and datasets will lead to transformative research? The answer being, there’s not really some resounding agreement. Possible answers Dr. Abbot suggests the approach of a deatiled cellular model of a mouse brain, however, as HBP has experienced, there is a challenge here with integrating biophysical modeling with levels of connectivity (gap junction, neuromodulation, etc.) An alternative approach is discussed as a brain activity map that bridges existing theories about different regions of the brain in modeling one activity in order to align existsing theories. The challenge here seems to be design. How does one actually assemble all these odds and ends. I thought this quote was interesting: In Silico (Fairhall 2021) “IARPA’s MICrONS program is […] a collaborative effort to reconstruct the connectome of a section of visual cortex whose activity has been characterized in vivo. By establishing the functional relevance of specific neurons, this project addresses some of the criticisms made of both the Blue Brain (Yong, 2019) and connectomics approaches.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 2" /><published>2021-11-14T13:16:13-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-14T13:16:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review2/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.02.26.433027v1.abstract&quot;&gt;Sparse balance: excitatory-inhibitory networks with small bias currents and broadly distributed synaptic weights
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=Ramin+Khajeh&amp;amp;oq=Ramin+Khajeh&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57.82j0j7&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;Ramin Khajeh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=rcb8W94AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=ca&quot;&gt;Francesco Fumarola&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://zuckermaninstitute.columbia.edu/larry-f-abbott-phd&quot;&gt;Larry F. Abbott&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Citation: Khajeh, Ramin, Francesco Fumarola, and L. F. Abbott. “Sparse balance: excitatory-inhibitory networks with small bias currents and broadly distributed synaptic weights.” bioRxiv (2021).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER&lt;/strong&gt; I am very interested in this part of computational neuroscience, but I’m a bit of a beginner to this topic. Some of the stuff here goes over my head, esp. the tractability of the gamma distribution in setting synaptic weights. If I got anything horribly wrong or you have any feedback please email me at zladd@berkeley.edu. Later I plan to add a feedback section using disqus at the botttom of each blog.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intro
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Neurons recieve a lot of excitatory input so there must be inhbitory balance. Some mechanism are cited as responsible for this:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Recurrent excitation&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Recurrent inhibition&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Feedfoward excitation&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;No evidence that feedforward excitaiton is particularly strong in these models.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;This is definitely new to me.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;States that
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;synaptic weight distributions have variance around $\frac{1}{\sqrt{k}}$ where $K$ is node in-degree.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;order of inhibitory input is around $\sqrt(K)$&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;and it’s generally cancelled by an excitatory input of equal magnitude, but they want to avoid this.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Suggests that without feedforward exc. input, there will be low firing rate but moves this evidence in argument for a sparser network, not a dense netowrk with low firing rate neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Getting rid of feedforward exc. means that synaptic distirbutions lose variance, so they suggest remedying this by making synaptic strength vary with a mean of $\frac{1}{\sqrt{K}}$ but then vary with order $\frac{1}{\sqrt{K}}$ this means total variance is now $\frac{\sqrt{K}}{\sqrt{K}}$ again (prev. it was $\frac{1}{\sqrt{k}}$)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;One part of this that I don’t understand is a formal mathematical definition for a &lt;em&gt;synaptic weight distribution&lt;/em&gt;. I think that for a more experienced reader, they will know what this means. My understanding is that this distribution will be a vector like $\bf{x} \in \mathbb{R^{K}}$ and this vector with the excitory input would follow something like $\bf{x_{1:\sqrt{K}}} \sim \mathcal{N}(\frac{1}{\sqrt{K}},1)$ (standard model –&amp;gt; variance == 1?) and the inihbitory component would be $\bf{x_{1:\sqrt{K}}} \sim \mathcal{N}(-\frac{1}{\sqrt{K}},1)$.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;there are a few things I here I would want to ask:
                &lt;ol&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;We have only accounted for $ 2 \times \sqrt{K}$ of the $K$ weights. Are the rest of the synaptic weights just 0?
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                      &lt;li&gt;honestly, I’m missing something here. I think all weights are accounted for, I just don’t know how.&lt;/li&gt;
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                  &lt;/li&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;Do these weights have unit variance?&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ol&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The model
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This part starts to clear up the questions above&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;They state that
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Sparse balance: excitatory-inhibitory networks with small bias currents and broadly distributed synaptic weights. (Khajeh 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Networks have currents $x_i$ for $i = 1 … N$ and firing rates $\phi(x_i)$ that obey
   \begin{equation}
   \Gamma_x \frac{dx_i}{dt} = -x_i - \sum\limits_j^N J_{ij}\phi(x_j) + I_0
   \end{equation} where $\phi$ is a nonlinear function and $J_{ij} \geq 0$&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I am not sure what $J_{ij}$ represents now. *note: it get’s explained a few sentences later. – they are i.i.d. weights.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Besides that, this function does a good job of clearly defining synaptic integration.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Considers tangenet vs. exponential nonlinear activation functions for $\phi$.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Simulation results
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;When excitatory input is set to $I_0 \sim \sqrt{K}$ the network has either sparse and high firing rate reponses (high variance), or dense and low firing rate responses (low variance).
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;this lines up nicely with what was introduced in the beginning and has a very clear inuitive interpretation. Nice!&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Then they dig in to some detailed numerical explanations for this effect.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Figure 1 is very clear :thumbsup:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;I was surprised to see that in panel G, the feedfoward input only had a small impact on the fraction of active neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sparse E/I balance lead to non-gaussian 0-skewed distribution of synaptic weights&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The authors state that these results represent a robust distribution of synaptic weights desipte not having any excitatory input.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Analysis of Sparse Balance Networks
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;here the authors explore high variance, low exc. input, sparse networks further using heavside non-linear response function.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;had to look this one up, but it’s basically a piecewise activaiton function where the gradient is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirac_delta_function&quot;&gt;dirac delta function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;weights drawn from $\text{gamma}(k, \theta)$&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Figure 3A would benefit from text titles on the figure, not just in the caption (at least for a reader like me lol I suck at reading figs).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What I got out of Fig. 3 is that heavside function lead to lower fraction of active neurons compared to tanh and exp. activation functions and thus a sparser netowrk. But that it also had a non-gaussian distribution of weights under the sparse condition.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Interesting point about having a larger $K$ or shape parameter for gamma, one might expect that the gamma function approximate gaussian function. But this is not the case with $\eta \sim \text{gamma}(\alpha, \theta)$.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I wonder if I understood that right?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;If feedforward bias is small  –&amp;gt; large synaptic variance required for robust fluctuation.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sparse Activity Arises from Network Dynamics
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;They use population averaged autocorrelation function to find out how much the weight distribution is affected by the previous weight distribution at some lag.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Autocorrelation decays faster for larger K (fig. 4).
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Sparse balance: excitatory-inhibitory networks with small bias currents and broadly distributed synaptic weights. (Khajeh 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;it is the dynamics of the recurrent synaptic inputs, not their size, that leads to sparse activity at large K&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mean Field Analysis
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Introduces a variable $m$ which is the mean-field approximation for $\bar{\phi}$&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Based on fuctions 7 and 11 (I think) they define closed form equation for $m$ in terms of gamma dist. shape parameter $\alpha$ as 
  \begin{equation}
  \alpha = \frac{mJ_0^2\sqrt(m)}{g^2}
  \end{equation}
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;$g^2$ comes from gamma dist. scale parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;considers several cases of computing autocorrelation of $\eta$ based on different sizes of $K$ and decorrealtion rate $\beta$.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;When $K$ is small, then $eta$ follows gamma distribution $\text{gamma}(\alpha, \theta)$ and then they can solve closed form mean field calcuation using integral.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;even at $K ~ 10^3$ this holds.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Then there’s a more complicated closed form calculation for $var(\eta)$ that I’m gonna skip over for now.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;involves decomposing the variance into quenched and time dependent.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;not very familiar with this decomposition. Maybe if I look into mean field decomp. more I will see.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fig. 5 just shows that this recover of gamma distribution parameters charcterizes weights and input parameter well. Again, clear and nice figure :thumbsup:&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sparse balance in E-I network
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;shows that &lt;em&gt;network properties&lt;/em&gt; shown for I network model also apply for E/I model, such as sparsity (frac. of neurons active) and firing rates.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Discussion
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Shows interesting network properties demonstrated in this anaylsis as a result of making feedforward excitation smaller.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Broadens out implications to real world instances where E/I ratio is similarly composed.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Interesting to point out this phenomenon in relating autocorrelation and network sparse responses seems to be a general effect.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Definitely incresed my interested in mean field theory.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Here is what I think is really the most fascinating takeway:
  &lt;strong&gt;“The large degree of variability in the synapses could route stimulus information along particular  paths across network neurons”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A reasonable claim that it is not just feedforward input that influences selective network responses but also recurrent synaptic input.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;The number of recurrent connections in the brain would support this idea. If there is so many recurrent networks, they must be doing something.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Ideas here build on some early work by M. Jordan cited in The Computational Brain by Terrence Sejnowski on using recurrent networks to identify shapes and the expressive power of &lt;em&gt;non-feedforward&lt;/em&gt; connections.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Granted, I haven’t actually read this 1998 work, just read the watered down example in Dr. Sejnowski’s book.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Sparse balance: excitatory-inhibitory networks with small bias currents and broadly distributed synaptic weights by Ramin Khajeh, Francesco Fumarola, Larry F. Abbott</summary></entry></feed>