<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-29T23:31:05-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alexander Ladd</title><subtitle>An amazing website.</subtitle><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Am I a Blogger?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/Am-I-a-Blogger/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Am I a Blogger?" /><published>2021-08-28T22:36:13-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-28T22:36:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/Am-I-a-Blogger</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/Am-I-a-Blogger/">&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of making my own personal website and as I am stapling posters to the walls and setting up furniture, I can’t help but think about how important the task at hand is. At the same time, I can’t help but think about equally unimportant it is. Clearly, I am a person who thinks a lot. Don’t confuse thinking a lot with being intelligent, proficient etc., most of the times, one clear line of reasoning is the winner. But I can’t help feeling two diverging narratives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first narrative is the cup half empty guy. When I think about the internet and doing anyhting on the internet, I think of the pareto distribution. Basically, I think that there are some sites that make up 85% of the traffic on the internet. For this group, think Amazon, Ebay, Facebook, Instagram. Then, I think there are another 10% of sites that are intermittently trafficked, but feel a little like a ghost town. For this group think club penguin, you might go on it ironically to relive the old days, but you aren’t checking it everyday to see how your puffles are doing (don’t get it? OK boomer). Finally, I’d put personal websites, resturant websites, and myspace in the last group – no one goes there unless they’ve fallen down a click hole, or they are really hungry and it’s past 8pm. And in the case of myspace, no one goes there ever I think. So that’s where this &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt; lands. The likely demographic to land here is probably my friends, potential hiring people, and co-wokers, but besides that the world will keep on spinning with or without my un-proofread &lt;em&gt;posts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything isn’t doom and gloom though, the reason I am here typing away is the second narrative. I started by putting portfolio stuff together on here, but now that I’ve painted some of the walls, I am sitting down and having a soda. In my moment of respite, I feel one significant reason to actually post thoughts that are in my head on this website. It’s simply that I wanted to remember how I felt about doing this. And not just posting this &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt;, but I wanted to remember how it felt to do a lot of things. I wanted to remember how it felt to publish my first paper, how it felt to graduate during a pandemic, and also stuff I thought about books I’ve read. In general there are things I felt like writing about in order to &lt;strong&gt;share them with myself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that I’ve consumed a lot of information in my life. But I am genuinely scared by how many things I’ve forgotten, how many times I’ve learned the same lessons over and over, and how little I actually know about myself. The great thing about writing is that you &lt;strong&gt;have&lt;/strong&gt; to form an opinon. You have no choice, you either have no opinion or you have no writing. The inception for writing this stuff comes from all the times I’ve discussed a book I’ve read but completely forgotten the content or my opinion of it. Other inspiration for doing this comes from version controlling my code. I can never remember what I have and haven’t changed, but a repository where the history is tracked is really satisfying. I know that for every monkey patch I leave in my code, there’s a commit where I add the comment # TODO: Remove Monkey Patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the lines of reason have converged and now you (I) know my thoughts on &lt;em&gt;posting&lt;/em&gt;. However,one closing remark. Several times while writing this, I cringed at writing the word &lt;em&gt;blog&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt like a blogger was someone who just their two cents in on everything as if their opinion deserved a pedestal (sure, call me a hater). I know this isn’t true, bloggers help moderate culture, they help our uphold our cultural agreement on avant garde art, tasty food, good music, and quality little furniture, to name a few. But addmitedly, except for normally toting the populist opinion, I am too much of an overthinker to be a blogger. So it is decided by me, for an audience of  &amp;lt; 50, that, no I’m not a blogger. Someday someone might call this a blog, and I’ll cringe again. But for now I’m leaping from thought to musing and then crawling towards a ponderance before running back to mute observation as the world remains too complex to draw the line a blogger draws. I am just hands on a keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t actually expect to even type that many things on here, but starting is better than never starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;club penguin picture,
inception picture
myspace
little furniture blog
&amp;lt;!– You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/ --&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I am in the process of making my own personal website and as I am stapling posters to the walls and setting up furniture, I can’t help but think about how important the task at hand is. At the same time, I can’t help but think about equally unimportant it is. Clearly, I am a person who thinks a lot. Don’t confuse thinking a lot with being intelligent, proficient etc., most of the times, one clear line of reasoning is the winner. But I can’t help feeling two diverging narratives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Am I a Blogger?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/blogger/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Am I a Blogger?" /><published>2020-09-28T14:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T14:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/blogger</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/blogger/">&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of making my own personal website and as I am stapling posters to the walls and setting up furniture, I can’t help but think about how important the task at hand is. At the same time, I can’t help but think about equally unimportant it is. Clearly, I am a person who thinks a lot. Don’t confuse thinking a lot with being intelligent, proficient etc., most of the times, one clear line of reasoning is the winner. But I can’t help feeling two diverging narratives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first narrative is the cup half empty guy. When I think about the internet and doing anyhting on the internet, I think of the pareto distribution. Basically, I think that there are some sites that make up 85% of the traffic on the internet. For this group, think Amazon, Ebay, Facebook, Instagram. Then, I think there are another 10% of sites that are intermittently trafficked, but feel a little like a ghost town. For this group think club penguin, you might go on it ironically to relive the old days, but you aren’t checking it everyday to see how your puffles are doing (don’t get it? OK boomer). Finally, I’d put personal websites, resturant websites, and myspace in the last group – no one goes there unless they’ve fallen down a click hole, or they are really hungry and it’s past 8pm. And in the case of myspace, no one goes there ever I think. So that’s where this &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt; lands. The likely demographic to land here is probably my friends, potential hiring people, and co-wokers, but besides that the world will keep on spinning with or without my un-proofread &lt;em&gt;posts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything isn’t doom and gloom though, the reason I am here typing away is the second narrative. I started by putting portfolio stuff together on here, but now that I’ve painted some of the walls, I am sitting down and having a soda. In my moment of respite, I feel one significant reason to actually post thoughts that are in my head on this website. It’s simply that I wanted to remember how I felt about doing this. And not just posting this &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt;, but I wanted to remember how it felt to do a lot of things. I wanted to remember how it felt to publish my first paper, how it felt to graduate during a pandemic, and also stuff I thought about books I’ve read. In general there are things I felt like writing about in order to &lt;strong&gt;share them with myself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that I’ve consumed a lot of information in my life. But I am genuinely scared by how many things I’ve forgotten, how many times I’ve learned the same lessons over and over, and how little I actually know about myself. The great thing about writing is that you &lt;strong&gt;have&lt;/strong&gt; to form an opinon. You have no choice, you either have no opinion or you have no writing. The inception for writing this stuff comes from all the times I’ve discussed a book I’ve read but completely forgotten the content or my opinion of it. Other inspiration for doing this comes from version controlling my code. I can never remember what I have and haven’t changed, but a repository where the history is tracked is really satisfying. I know that for every monkey patch I leave in my code, there’s a commit where I add the comment # TODO: Remove Monkey Patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the lines of reason have converged and now you (I) know my thoughts on &lt;em&gt;posting&lt;/em&gt;. However,one closing remark. Several times while writing this, I cringed at writing the word &lt;em&gt;blog&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt like a blogger was someone who just their two cents in on everything as if their opinion deserved a pedestal (sure, call me a hater). I know this isn’t true, bloggers help moderate culture, they help our uphold our cultural agreement on avant garde art, tasty food, good music, and quality little furniture, to name a few. But addmitedly, except for normally toting the populist opinion, I am too much of an overthinker to be a blogger. So it is decided by me, for an audience of  &amp;lt; 50, that, no I’m not a blogger. Someday someone might call this a blog, and I’ll cringe again. But for now I’m leaping from thought to musing and then crawling towards a ponderance before running back to mute observation as the world remains too complex to draw the line a blogger draws. I am just hands on a keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t actually expect to even type that many things on here, but starting is better than never starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;club penguin picture,
inception picture
myspace
little furniture blog&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I am in the process of making my own personal website and as I am stapling posters to the walls and setting up furniture, I can’t help but think about how important the task at hand is. At the same time, I can’t help but think about equally unimportant it is. Clearly, I am a person who thinks a lot. Don’t confuse thinking a lot with being intelligent, proficient etc., most of the times, one clear line of reasoning is the winner. But I can’t help feeling two diverging narratives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s not on a Grad School App</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/grad1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s not on a Grad School App" /><published>2020-09-28T14:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T14:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/grad1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/grad1/">&lt;p&gt;As somone who has applied two consecutive years to graduate schools, I’ve put a lot of thought about what I can and can’t communicate on my personal statement. At first, two great pieces of advice as far as writing a personal statement appear to conflict with eachother – 1. tell a story and 2. don’t write up your resume. In reality, there is a golden spot that manages to tell a cohesive story without bullet pointing your resume and instead capturing some of the magic that made me want to puruse a graduate degree and a career in research. For me, here are some of the bigger picture &lt;em&gt;feelings&lt;/em&gt; about this. I say feelings, because at the end of the day, that’s whats missing from a resume. It’s the feeling, emotion, ugliness and beauty that all gets chemically washed out and dumped into a CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Owning a Research Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is really something to be said about a project that has your fingerprints all over it. On one hand it’s awesome, because the more it becomes you the more comfortable you feel navigating it. There is a very close analogy between a house and a research project, too big and alone and you get lost, but too small and you get cramped. The code, experiments, and data make up the furniture and decorations in your house, and we all know how quickly a small mess can turn into a big mess if things aren’t handled well. However, there is a famous tradeoff between making things pretty and making things quickly (cite). Clean solutions are beautiful, but a major turning point in my research / programming career was accepting that messy solutions (like try/except in python) can actually create a cleaner overall codebase. This is why owning a research project means owning it for all its imperfections, for example all the things you wrote knowing there might’ve been a better implementation. It also means owning it for all the great features your project has too, like when somone asks you to make a change or run a new experiment and you launch the thing five minutes after they ask because you knew just what lines to change. Finally, there are two other interesting feelings here. One is going back over old code and jumping in, sometimes it can be scary and we have this tendency to set and forget, but as an engineer it’s challenging but critical to go into the belly of the beast (that you created!) and set things straight. The second is writing new code. Once you’ve written thousands of lines of code, sometimes we have a tendency to rest on our laurels and not push our tools any further. And to that I respond, push it til it breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sisyphus
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is the best one, the golden egg of research to me and one of the main reasons I love what I do.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">As somone who has applied two consecutive years to graduate schools, I’ve put a lot of thought about what I can and can’t communicate on my personal statement. At first, two great pieces of advice as far as writing a personal statement appear to conflict with eachother – 1. tell a story and 2. don’t write up your resume. In reality, there is a golden spot that manages to tell a cohesive story without bullet pointing your resume and instead capturing some of the magic that made me want to puruse a graduate degree and a career in research. For me, here are some of the bigger picture feelings about this. I say feelings, because at the end of the day, that’s whats missing from a resume. It’s the feeling, emotion, ugliness and beauty that all gets chemically washed out and dumped into a CV.</summary></entry></feed>