<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-12T11:52:42-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alexander Ladd</title><subtitle>An amazing website.</subtitle><author><name>Alexander Ladd</name><email>zladd@berkeley.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Review 31: Noninvasive Brain–Machine Interfaces for Robotic Devices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review31/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 31: Noninvasive Brain–Machine Interfaces for Robotic Devices" /><published>2022-06-11T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review31</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review31/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/brain-implant&quot;&gt;Noninvasive Brain–Machine Interfaces for Robotic Devices&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=U2N9FlcAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Luca Toning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ece.utexas.edu/people/faculty/jose-del-r-millan&quot;&gt;José del R. Millán&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonin, Luca, and José del R. Millán. “Noninvasive brain–machine interfaces for robotic devices.” Annual Review of Control, Robotics, and Autonomous Systems 4 (2021): 191-214.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First this from the abstract: “. We found that BMIs are used mostly to drive devices for navigation (e.g., telepresence mobile robots), with BMI paradigms based mainly on exogenous stimulation, and the majority of brain-actuated robots adopt a discrete control strategy,”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main focus of brain-machine interfaces, or BMIs, is to restore motor functions for those with damaged pathways or motor dysfunction.
eg; brain-controlled cursor movement, keyboards + typing, remote-controlled devices.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Not just a plug and play engineering problem, we should think about how to generate effective control signals as well.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Paper roadmap: introduce closed-loop system -&amp;gt; turn to main modalities of interaction/control -&amp;gt; provide an overview of 86 works over the past 15 years -&amp;gt; lay out challenges and future directions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Closed Loop of a Brain-Machine Interface: A Mutual Learning Interaction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Here is a high level description of Fig 1.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Brain activity is elicited and recorded.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Endogenous: user voluntarily engages activity in some mental task.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Exogenous: user is presented stimuli and correlates of brain activity are measured during this task.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Features are extracted.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Control.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;This block in the flow is complicated. Suffice it to say that this part is a signal handed to a robotic device.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Online feedback.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;User &lt;em&gt;sees&lt;/em&gt; behavior and deems it rewarding / not rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Rinse and Repeat.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two key considerations for this loop to work:
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Toning 2021&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Two concepts therefore become essential in the design of the BMI closed loop: a fast response by the robot to the user’s intention, in order to allow fine and reactive control over the device (Section 4), and a bidirectional interaction between the robot and BMI, in order to trigger and exploit the robot intelligence and thus support the user in performing complex actions (Section 5).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ultimately this seems like communication bandwidth between the human/animal (affector) and the controlled device (effector).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invasive and Noninvasive Acquisition Techniques
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Noninvasive BMIs can access either electrocorticogram signals (EEG) or hemodynamic activity (bloodflow) like seen in fMRIs.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;EEG has an advantage temporally but fMRI has an advantage spatially.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signal Processing and Feature Extraction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lots of filtering happens in non-invasive BCI so that we can increase signal to noise ratio.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Filter DC component.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Spatial filters.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Low dimensional reductions of data.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hilbert transform, FFT transform, wavelet decomposition.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feature Selection and Classification Algorithms
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;16 channels with 4-48hz resolution result in 340+ features to potentially consider.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;During calibration channels that are discriminative or particularly relevant to functional neural correlates are selected in feature selection.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After online/control phase, the decoder is then used for offline discriminant classification.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;SVM, Gaussian +/ kernel models.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human-In-The-Loop: Interaction Modalities in Brain-Machine Interfaces
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exogenous paradigms
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Steady-state evoked potential (SSEP) based BMIs: present several visual stimuli to target (like a flashing light) and the user can guide control by fixing their eyes on a specific target, which corresponds to an action in a remote-controlled robotic device.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;P300 signals are evoked after some anomalistic pattern is observed. It’s hard to see how users picking out infrequent patterns or letters can lead to goal-directed control of a robotic arm. I’d have to look into the Farwell–Donchin spellers task.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Error-related signals can be used to increase robustness for BMI applications.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Endogenous Paradigms
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Event-related localized changes in frequency, or an increment or decrement in EEG.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;$\mu$ and $\beta$ bands of activity specifically related to motor imagination.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Event-related synchronization or desynchronization.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Task-specific modulation is represented as a marker on a screen, which is important because the capacity for the user to receive continuous feedback about cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Figure 2 quick jot.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Surprisingly, relative fisher scores for features were very stable over different frequencies.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Also 12hz ($\mu$ band) was particularly identifiable.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Quadratic boundary used for foot movement v.s. hand movement discrimination.
                &lt;ul&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;This is also surprising as the feature representation is projected to a $\mathbb{R}^2$ subspace which is very compact. Yet a basic quadratic discrimator works!&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Signal trajectory needs to converge past boundary to be classified. In one trajectory, neither hand nor foot is detected.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control strategies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BMI control is often combined with a corresponding control strategy from the stimulated device.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;While most systems use discrete control in continuous v.s. discrete control, there is the potential for both.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Discrete is slower and has lower bandwidth.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Continuous control is interesting but not as studied.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;One of the interesting apps is as a continuous driving signal. The other app is the stabilization of discrete commands.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EEG patterns are non-stationary.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robot in the Loop: Sharing the Intelligence
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Since many tasks (eg; robotic arm) reaching with non-invasive (and invasive?) BMI is pretty difficult, the devices are often equipped with (or learn) fine level control and stabilization.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two approaches to machine autonomous control: 1. user looks at a spot and the machine takes responsibility for guiding it there using whatever control sequences it pleases or 2. user can offer more granular directions, like turning a wheelchair using a finite state machine (Iturrate et al. (52) qtd. in Toning 2021).
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I am looking forward to hearing what the challenges for 2 are where. There seems to be a bottleneck in terms of how much bandwidth there is for control, just like in the case of continuous decoding.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sequential control passed between human and robotic arm during grasping task. Human uses menu-based assistance to guide arm and then uses BMI to complete grasping action.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared control ultimately seems like a nice future direction since humans can have higher-level control and robot can have lower-level control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Subversion of explicit BMI signaling using detection of error-related signals in BMI.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;An error-based override allows the robot to re-interpret the signal.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current Applications
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Devices, Interaction Modalities, and Control Strategies
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Here the authors give a nice breakdown of mobile control studies: “ brain-controlled mobile robots for telepresence are the type that is most common in the literature (Figure 4a), representing 38.4% of the reviewed studies, followed by powered wheelchairs (22.1%), robotic arms (19.8%), lower limb and upper limb exoskeletons (9.3% and 7.0%, respectively), and quadcopters (3.5%).” (Toning 2021).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;See figure:
   &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tonin1.png&quot; alt=&quot;bmi overview&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Brain-controlled robotic arms are studied in several different studies.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Surprisingly only 16.3% of studies included participants that had motor defecits.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Challenges and Future Directions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Integration between BMI and robots is in early days. Normally, the robot is just seen as an actuator.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overcoming commitment to exogenous systems and developing endogenous and self-paced systems has more deploy-ability but comes with challenges for calibration and user mental capacity to focus on this kind of control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The biggest challenge is that most studies are not conducted in coordination with the end-users.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Which biases the design of the device and calibration/training strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A lot of the time, training phases can take weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Applications in navigation and manipulation may not be the most prioritized use case for the end-user. It would be best to coordinate with patients whom BMI researchers aim to help in order to re-contextualize what their priorities are in order to get better alignment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Noninvasive Brain–Machine Interfaces for Robotic Devices by Luca Toning and José del R. Millán</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 30: Eavesdropping on the Brain With 10,000 Electrodes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review30/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 30: Eavesdropping on the Brain With 10,000 Electrodes" /><published>2022-06-05T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-05T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review30</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review30/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/brain-implant&quot;&gt;Eavesdropping on the Brain With 10,000 Electrodes&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imecitf.com/2021/health/speakers/barun-dutta-chief-scientist-sts-imec&quot;&gt;Barun Dutta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dutta, Barun. “Eavesdropping on the Brain With 10,000 Electrodes.” IEEE Spectrum (2022)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is interesting because this article is released by Barun Dutta, one of the principal investigators of the neuropixels devices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hook begins with the infamous brain-computer metaphor.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This “brain is a computer” comparison is tired, but this hook works well anyway because it points to the really astounding fact that the brain only requires 20 watts of power.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The introduction sets the stage for introducing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imec-int.com/en&quot;&gt;Imec&lt;/a&gt; importance of large-scale recordings of individual neurons and a freely moving animal. This company does some really awesome things with nano and digital technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name “neuropixels” is explained as a field potential recording system that relies on signal processing, kind of like a camera.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also see that neuropixels aims to tackle some of the issues located physically deeper in the brain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels 1.0 has a single shank and 1000 electrodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels 2.0 has four shanks with 1280 electrodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With 3.0 they claim they are moving along an exponential growth curve for BCI recording.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is encouraging to see Imec’s efforts in materials sciences in CMOS fabrication.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;low impedance electro-ceramic shanks sound more durable and much less likely to have electrical discharge.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I find this quote surprising:
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dutta (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;“the thousandfold difference in elasticity between CMOS shanks and brain tissue”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;because I had no idea that even the most flexible shanks are still this level of magnitude more rigid than brain tissue. This  highlights the importance of these efforts in materials sciences and electrical engineering.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2D readouts help power stabilization algorithm that allows the long-term tracking of specific neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new neuropixels device also features a smaller head-stage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;30 kilohertz sampling rate is very high. I wonder if anyone makes the argument that a higher sampling rate could ever be needed. I think at this resolution one could even analyze fast activating channel dynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “pixel” or neuron recording count is predicted to leap 50,000 - 100,000 neurons.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Big if true.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels 1 has 1000 recording sites and then Neuropixels 2 has 6000 recording sites, so a projection of 50k is bold.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall, the pace of development is astounding but in my opinion “Moore’s law” is a mischaracterization. Here’s why:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;So far we’ve observed one cycle and there was a 6x increase in recording sites, which is technically in line with the trend. However, this characterization of exponential growth would need to be sustained over multiple cycles… I think it is just too early to call.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Also, 1.0 and 2.0 don’t have that much of a difference in recording fidelity. 2.0 gets the increase in recording sites using more shanks and better tracking algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;While the advent of these areas of development is notable, I wonder if we see sustained progress in these domains or if new features can be added that will enable increasing recording sites in other ways.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Eavesdropping on the Brain With 10,000 Electrodes by Barun Dutta</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 29: Emergence of Coordinated Neural Dynamics Underlies Neuroprosthetic Learning and Skillful Control</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review29/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 29: Emergence of Coordinated Neural Dynamics Underlies Neuroprosthetic Learning and Skillful Control" /><published>2022-05-28T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-28T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review29</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review29/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627317300405&quot;&gt;Emergence of Coordinated Neural Dynamics Underlies Neuroprosthetic Learning and Skillful Control&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.actingbrain.com/vivek-athalye&quot;&gt;Vivek Athalye&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Faculty/Homepages/carmena.html&quot;&gt;Jose Carmena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athalye, Vivek R., et al. “Emergence of coordinated neural dynamics underlies neuroprosthetic learning and skillful control.” Neuron 93.4 (2017): 955-970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pretty cool that this article is OA.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This work demonstrates how variance decreases in M1 neuronal population during skillful acquistion using brain machine interface (BMI).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intro
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The fact that movement variability decreases across trials during point and click task suggests that there is some population of neurons generating the activity behind stable control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;So they try to identify some of these neurons using a BMI recording device attached to around 15 neurons and use mathematical transforms to get low dimensional representation of neural trajectories.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Novel task so subjects must start by exploring the action space. But eventually their performance on the task improves. How does this happen?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are three perspectives introduced:
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Independent neuron learning: controller inputs come directly from each neuron.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Constrained network learning: controller inputs come from sets of neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Flexible network learning: controller inputs comes from a mix of direct activation and set activation.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Matrix factor analysis will help disambiguate between these approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Experiment parameters:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Variability time scale is ~ 1 second.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Decoder time scale is 100 ms.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Center out BMI reaching task.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Decoder gives upper limb movements to xy cursor position on a screen.
Signal-specific readout space drives activity.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;signal alignment – 0 being subspaces match and 1 being they are orthogonal between epochs.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;amount of valid signals – how many readout signals actually have valid positions.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Results
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Authors propose variance changes in control happen between neuron private variance and neuron shared variance.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And that these can be composed into two covariance factors and that firing rate be the mean.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Then we will have $x = \mathcal{N}(\mu, \Sigma^{total} = \Sigma^{shared} + \Sigma^{private})$&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a visualization of the evolution of cursor trajectory which was striking.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Success rate, % of correct answers increase over trials and the project (workspace position) begins to become increasingly similar to a converged upon representation.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skillful_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skillful_legend1.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’m interested in specifically how they generate this low-dimensional representation. I guess they are probably using PCA and this is how they can calculate orthogonality etc. There are a lot of dimensional reduction methods though. I didn’t check the STAR methods.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Private variance: diagonal terms. within neuron variance of spike train.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared variance: off-diagonal covariance that represents the pairwise similarity between binned spike trains.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared variance increasingly drives movement across trials.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main shared variance begins to align as epochs increase and success rate increases. This suggests that alignment of shared variance in neuron firing rates drives consolidated learning.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Private variance also aligns and drives cursor movement but more so in the earlier trials.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skillful_fig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skillful_legend2.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As such, the authors suggest that the private variance serves an early exploratory role and the shared variance had more contribution on skillful control in support of flexible network learning hypothesis.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main shared space aligns with readout space making shared variance more effective in producing skillful movements.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Magnitude growth and re-alignemnt both increase for main shared variance over epochs.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;re-alignment is the distance between successive subspsaces (I think?).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Magnitude growth seems like it’s just the magnitude of the shared variance or the magnitude of the readout variance.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skillful3.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussion
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neuroprosthetic learning studies provide intriguing evidence that the brain can solve the credit assignment problem by specifically adapting neurons that contribute to the global error signal provided by the prosthetic cursor.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’m not so surprised that the magnitude of the shared signal norm increases across trials because the BCI reward feedback is likely to introduce some change in the scale of a variance measure.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Athalye et al. 2017&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We hypothesize that the population finds this solution by selecting particular shared inputs that produce goal-achieving activity within a characteristic manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BMI manifold emerged that contained consolidated neural trajectories for skillful control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; like this final quote for a few future reasearch question:
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Athalye et al. 2017&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Future decoders might benefit from more detailed models of neural population dynamics and how they change with learning. Indeed, a recent algorithmic approach yielded significant performance improvement by modeling neural population dynamics underlying natural movements to decode the subject’s intent while moving freely (Kao et al., 2015). Perhaps neural learning can help to generalize this approach to immobile patients, as we found coordinated neural dynamics can be consolidated over training in the absence of overt movement. Given our findings that main shared variance achieves better performance than total activity in simulations (Figures S6B–S6D), a performance-motivated extension would be to design a decoder that is able to denoise neural observations based on learned neural dynamics (Shenoy and Carmena, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In my opinion, each sentence here can be taken apart and used to brainstorm future research directions that are related. There is an interesting web of interesting connections here.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Emergence of Coordinated Neural Dynamics Underlies Neuroprosthetic Learning and Skillful Control by Vivek Athalye and Jose Carmena</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 28: Four ethical priorities for neurotechnologies and AI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review28/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 28: Four ethical priorities for neurotechnologies and AI" /><published>2022-05-14T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-14T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review28</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review28/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/551159a&quot;&gt;Four ethical priorities for neurotechnologies and AI
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=G0WcJagAAAAJ&quot;&gt;Rafael Yuste&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://phil.washington.edu/people/sara-goering&quot;&gt;Sara Goering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yuste, Rafael, et al. “Four ethical priorities for neurotechnologies and AI.” Nature 551.7679 (2017): 159-163.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While full integration of neurotechnology into human life may take decades, it is critical to think about the ethical applications now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The morningside group is comprised of neurotech companies, academic labs, and intl. brain projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The existing ethics guidlines, such as Declariation of Helsinki in 1964, Belmont report, and Asilomar AI report, don’t cover many of the issues that are raised by BCI technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a very cool tidbit:
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;(Yuste &amp;amp; Goering 2017)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, researchers at Duke University in Durham, North Carolina, have shown that three monkeys with electrode implants can operate as a ‘brain net’ to move an avatar arm collaboratively.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/srep10767&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This BrainNet paper is one I am really interested in reading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DARPA Neural Engineering Project that aims to implant 1 million electrodes and selectively stimulates up to 100k neurons. The University of Freiburg in Germany is using EEG signals to decode motor planning activity to control robots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The four ethical priorities:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Privacy and consent: This concern has been pervasive throughout all types of recent technological advancements. There are many researchers working on what makes a system secure, but keeping data secure has proven to be a comparably large challenge as well. Often times data breaches that would occur in neurotech may use external data to draw connections that might allow them to identify individuals based on neural activity. Furthermore, many potential exploitative practices can extend from the centralization of neural data. The authors pose multiple mitigation strategies, but I really strongly agree with the strategy of not allowing the centralized storage of human neural data from BMI devices. While this may limit how devices can be developed, for now, it seems like a central safeguard from potentially disastrous data breaches.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agency / Identity: This concern caught me off guard because I hadn’t considered it much at all until I read this. Simply put, BMI devices can blue the line of how much agency they can attribute to certain actions. In this way, BMI devices can interfere with someone’s sense of identity in a negative way. I also found the potential mitigation strategies here less satisfying, although I don’t have any better ideas. I am in support for drafting a constitution of “neurorights” but I don’t see how this would help those with issues in BMI affected identity. Better yet would be a fast safeguard in each device to immediately shut off its functioning if needed. The reason I advocate for this is that the user should have complete autonomy over when they use the device and when it is inactive. This does open the device up to hacking. Also this kind of on/off switch might not be possible due to negative consequences from terminating the tight feedback loop between device and person. Regardless, I generally advocate that BMI functionality should be treated more like glasses and less like a pacemaker so that users will never feel completely trapped with the BMI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Augmentation: This is a very futuristic concern, but also one that should be considered now. At this point, the weaponization and militaristic augmentation of BMI devices are not major concerns. Though in the future they may be. To steer BMI devices on the right path, the authors argue for the establishment of a neurotechnology geneva convention style agreement about what research and applications can be ethically conducted using BMI devices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bias: Just like ML systems nowadays are biased by negative aspects of their data, such as hate speech in text datasets or lack of representation in image datasets, BMI devices can further perpetuate societal inequalities. To prevent this, it is necessary to open source data, algorithms, user research groups, and design. Through the proper channels, civil liberties and nonprofit auditors should be able to inspect the scientific practices of companies or groups doing neural engineering. Representation of diverse needs and circumstances should be considered in thorough research feature testing, quality testing, and design. Recently, there have been many failures in preventing biased models and disinformation on major technology platforms, so the future for this will be challenging.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving forward:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This kind of review provides great directions for moving forward; including widespread adoption of a Hippocratic oath for neuro engineers and ethical discussion sections for labs. While training certainly helps move employees and individuals in the right direction, in my opinion, the field would benefit from the following: (1) Some kind of agency responsible for oversight of responsible use of BMI devices. (2) Forums / conferences / journals for neuroethics. (3) Some kind of open sourced / democratized code for precedents.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Four ethical priorities for neurotechnologies and AI by Rafael Yuste and Sara Goering</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 27: Parsing learning in networks using brain–machine interfaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review27/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 27: Parsing learning in networks using brain–machine interfaces" /><published>2022-05-14T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-14T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review27</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review27/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0959438817301642?casa_token=mBc7NGX5SMoAAAAA:_u-U4AxlrusxSveU-DitDvaDjvUhYixFrO7ZuZs4B0iIa6Dy0xmDc6Za4MZYRqBFf8E7IiwcVOQ&quot;&gt;Parsing learning in networks using brain-machine
interfaces&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.ece.uw.edu/orsborn_amy/&quot;&gt;Amy Orsborn&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://as.nyu.edu/content/nyu-as/as/faculty/bijan-pesaran.html&quot;&gt;Bijan Pesaran&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orsborn, Amy L., and Bijan Pesaran. “Parsing learning in networks using brain-machine interfaces.” Current opinion in neurobiology 46 (2017): 76-83.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Motor BMIs: repurpose neural activity to control the movement of a device.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Give the brain a new functionality that the brain can adapt to use.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BMIs also allow us to study the mechanisms of learning for neuroscience.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Yet, while there is work showing how BMIs can enable learning, the above point about the underlying neural mechanisms is still mostly unknown.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These BCI papers all have really great figure 1s.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/r27_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This figure presents three different perspectives on closed-loop Motor BCI systems.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;A: This is the main BCI closed-loop and very similar to the previous review.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;B: Is interesting because it shows the affector/effector dynamics. It is also interesting because it shows that some nodes from the network should send a signal to the actuator while some nodes indirectly signal by not signaling. Finally, it shows that some external reward drives closed-loop BCI learning – which is important because this shows the progression of closed-loop BCI device is dependent on the perceived reward system in the brain.
                &lt;ul&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;External reward normally just processed through vision. If you control a cursor on a screen successfully you will see that.&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;C: Shows what points can use learning feedback and what learning/error signal they require to improve. BCI closed-loop system can be improved in strategy/selection of motor plans and in the “internal” model… which I take to mean the decoder.
                &lt;ul&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;As I start to become more specific in my focus on BCI, this kind of distinction can help inform future reading/research directions.&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Interesting point I did not know:
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Orsborn et al. 2017&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;“visual information is highly dominant over proprioceptive information” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.143.3606.594&quot;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I guess this is probably really context-dependent though.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Combining command nodes for BMI in a different way allows researchers to investigate the relationship between BMI learning and natural learning.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Figure 2
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Feedback rate and control rate increases both increase success rate for in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms13825&quot;&gt;Shanechi et al.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;BMIs can investigate sites of learning around probes. For example, optogenetic stimulation near electrode recording sites can help study neural mechanisms of feedback learning.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The conclusion is very concise so I’ll add this final part here.
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Orsborn et al. 2017&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Since BMIs tap into our brain’s innate ability to learn, understanding learning in BMIs will ultimately advance clinical applications of this technology. In the search for effective treatments, we may find that interfaces that harness learning can improve the patient experience compared with those which simply accommodate learning.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Parsing learning in networks using brain-machine interfaces by Amy Orsborn and Bijan Pesaran</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 26: A control-theoretic approach to brain-computer interface design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review26/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 26: A control-theoretic approach to brain-computer interface design" /><published>2022-05-07T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-07T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review26</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review26/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smithlab.net/~schase/docs/zhang_acc_2016.pdf&quot;&gt;A control-theoretic approach to brain-computer interface design&lt;/a&gt; by Yin Zhang and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmu.edu/bme/People/Faculty/profile/schase.html&quot;&gt;Steven Chase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhang, Yin, and Steven M. Chase. “A control-theoretic approach to brain-computer interface design.” 2016 American Control Conference (ACC). IEEE, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A challenge in brain computer interface (BCI) design is mapping from population activity to BCI actuation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This paper proposes using optimal control theory to formulate and improve BCI usability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main algorithmic proposals for mapping population activity to behavior:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;linear estimators&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kalman filters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Particle filters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neural net decoders&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;point process filters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;kernel based techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That is a lot of potential approaches. The nuances of the application would be required in order to sort them out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MLE approach to BCI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Velocity kalman filter defined as: $\mathbf{y_t} = B\mathbf{v_t}^* + \mathbf{\epsilon_t
  }$ where $\mathbf{y_t}$ are $n$ neuron’s firing rates and $\mathbf{v_t}$ is the velocity of a prosethetic effector.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This is clear mathematically but I don’t know what a prosthetic effector is.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It seems like some implant that would drive neuron firing rates.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A second assumption is that this velocity changes smoothly over time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Using these two assumptions: BCI control reduces to Bayesian inference over how this velocity results in firing rates.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I thought there would be more here since after this level of inference you’d still have to infer the previous problem of spike activity mapping to actions.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Using the above equations and the a posteriori estimate of $p(\mathbf{v_t} \mid y_1 … y_t)$, one can create a time dependent state update rule for a BCI controlled cursor position $\mathbf{p_t}$ using $\mathbf{v_t}$.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;notation here is confusing because I thought y was in $\mathbb{R}^n$ as a firing frequency for n neurons. I take it the authors mean to use the 1 - t as $y$ at some previous recording time t.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This also answered my previous point about mpaping from $\mathbf{v_t}$ to actual actions.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;While estimation based decoder control has remarkable progress in enabling cursor speed w/ in a factor of 2 of a natural limb, there are still some aspects that can be improved:
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Only decoders that correspond to simple physical systems work well.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Estimation framework assumes static tuning but performance in closed-loop systems over time is often very different and offline decoders may not work well in long term.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Biomemtic decoders are not guaranteed optimal. Translating signals in terms of basic human motor movements are not necessairly the best way to solve control problems.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Authors make 3 assumptions about the brain as optimal controller:
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The brain is emitting control signals that minimize some cost function.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Primary cortex activity is a direct representation of these signals.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;End goal result of learning is to produce the optimal control signals of a given effector.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;These assumptions have helped me understand a lot of what the paper is previously trying to build to.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Mainly, what I see now that I did not before is why the signal estimation approach is limiting and why understanding motor cotrex signals as effector signals is so important. I believe this is because control theory allows a framework for much more specific definitions of control when the goal is reconstructing effector signals instead of predicting movement. Predicting movement is often a more vague problem for a decoder while fine-grained analysis of how brain signals enable optimal control in reaching for example is much more specific.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bci_schematic.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I really like this figure since it is a straightforward diagram of the control model here.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It shows where that control signals feed into the plant for state updates in decoder.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;$x$ as cursor state, $u$ as control signal, and $J(u)$ as cost function for signal $u$.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Optimal cost is $J^*  = J^(u^*)$, plant parameters are $\phi$&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;$\phi$ determines the usefulness of BCI based on how it minimizes cost function.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Not so sure what $H_p$ and $H_v$ mean as spring like properties of the plant and viscous properties. Are these from control theory?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BCI plant system dyanmics
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/r26_e1.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Quadratic cost function used  in motor learning studies
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/r26_e2.png&quot; alt=&quot;bci schematic&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Normally I like to use latex to write out he equations in the paper but I don’t wan’t to the \bmatrix formatting today.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First solve forward control problem of optimizing $H_p$ and $H_t$.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Linear quadratic regulator gives minmial cost under optimal policy: $J*(H_p,H_t) = tr(P_0,X_0)$.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;are $H_p$ and $H_t$ suppoed to be $H_p^&lt;em&gt;$ and $H_t^&lt;/em&gt;$, the optimal conditions in order to get J*?
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Zhang 2016 on simulation results for this paper:&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;In one sense, these results might seem trivial: the optimal 2D linear BCI plant is an integrator that provides no resistance on the inputs. This is an intuitive solution given
that we assumed no bias in the control signals and further assumed a minimal effort constraint. In another sense, the results are quite surprising: the optimal dynamics identified through this approach to BCI design are qualitatively different from those of the typical BCI decoder, the VKF. In fact, the parameters identified with our method fall outside of the allowable parameters of a VKF.&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">A control-theoretic approach to brain-computer interface design by Yin Zhang and Steven Chase</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 25: Plug-and-play control of a brain-computer interface through neural map stabilization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 25: Plug-and-play control of a brain-computer interface through neural map stabilization" /><published>2022-04-30T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-30T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review25</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review25/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-020-0662-5&quot;&gt;Plug-and-play control of a brain-computer interface through neural map stabilization
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://gangulylab.org/people.html&quot;&gt;Daniel Silversmith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silversmith, Daniel B., et al. “Plug-and-play control of a brain-computer interface through neural map stabilization.” Nature Biotechnology 39.3 (2021): 326-335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having recently read higher-level overviews of BCIs, reading this paper in Nature Biotech will be especially relevant but more specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;180 channel electrocorticography (ECoG) implant in a paralyzed individual enabled stable monitoring of signals.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Long-term closed loop adaptation updates decoder weights over several days, thus updating map and plug and play control.
Intro&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Currently, 30 min daily recalibration results in variability in performance and decreased decoding performance in the long-term.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ECoG PNP control was achieved using an interface that updates within-session instead via closed-loop decoder adaptation (CLDA) and potentially over longer terms (ltCDA).
Results&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fig. 1
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;ECoG signal comes from a few brain regions: S1, M1 , PMC, PMV, SMA.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kalman Filter&lt;/strong&gt; decoder weights.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;There are a few aspects that are different between ltCLDA and daily initialization:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Time to taget increased, though it is hard to tell by how much as I can’t see mean values in the intervals.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;ITR shows clear increase during ltCDA.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Convergence of decoder weights is faster using ltCDA.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Time to target decreases from 18 to 6 seconds with tight error bounds.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I do not understand box diagram in fig H. Are the outwward pointing arrows for CNS and KF pipeline outputs?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weights are general orthogonal at the start of each dailty initializaiton, so pooling weights over days hurt model performance.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ltCDA resulted in stable convergence of decoder weights across sessions instead.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Higher half-life values (history length used in weight updates) led to better fixed control and more stable weight convergence.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some weights exhibiting low magnitude or common trends may be redundant and enables sparseness.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fig. 2
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A lot more variance in decoder map weights for daily initialization method.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;As the days go on, the orthogonality of the weights seems to decrease.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;mu weights decrease w/ linear trends and gamma2 weights increase w/ linear trend.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sparsity/weight pruning is pretty shocking with the 25% of the weights verison having a very similar time to target.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fig. 3
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Daily calibration had higher circular sd across channels in preferred direction (PD) task.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Decoder weight magnitude correlated to circular SD of PD.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;gamma2 weights are stable from day 36+ and it is visually confirmed.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;All weights show some trend toward stable convergence after day 18+, which is really interesting because it suggests long-term improvement with ltCLDA method.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fig. 4
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;ltCDA to Fixed Decoder swap at day 206 + 28 recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;both ltCDA and CLDA after reset seem to have stable weights.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Decoder weights angle is roughly 45 degrees after reset.
  Fig. 5&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Point and click task where cursor path and bits per second information rate are tracked.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Weights seem much sparser for click map.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I wonder how they will look for less convergent features.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Neural state needs to cross click threshold.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Everyday, after the cursor is in target area, stable clicking within 1 sec.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No significant drop in performance during PnP sessions (plug and play = no recalibration).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decoder reinitialization had 45-degree weight angle change but then converge back to 0.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussion
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ltCDA is an important example of weights being carried over a long time constant.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CLDA based on coadaptation can rapidly allow skilled control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Task-related manifolds can be remarkably stable.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Results indicate the feasibility of PnP.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Plug-and-play control of a brain-computer interface through neural map stabilization by Daniel Silversmith.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 24:The brain-reading devices helping paralysed people to move, talk and touch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 24:The brain-reading devices helping paralysed people to move, talk and touch" /><published>2022-04-23T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review24</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review24/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-01047-w?utm_medium=Social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=nature&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter#Echobox=1650446178&quot;&gt;The brain-reading devices helping paralysed people to move, talk and touch
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liamdrew.net/about&quot;&gt;Liam Drew&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brain-computer interface clinical trials for paralysis where the patient uses thoughts to operate a computer application moving a robotic arm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Johnson, a volunteer for the new neurotech, reports that he can move a mouse on a screen using BCI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Johnson is 1 of 35 individuals who have had a BCI implanted.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This number seems surprisingly low. I wouldn’t expect more than 1000 though.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black Rock Neurotech in Salt Lake City, Utah produces a lot of these devices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2006 Landmark paper where Dr. Leigh Hochberg et al. teach a man to move a cursor using robotic arms and was the first of a multicenter set of trials called BrainGate which continues today.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requires decoding algorithms to match neural data to actions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A major goal is to restore motor independence in people who have lost ability in moving their limbs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bypass central nervous system by directly stimulating muscles responsible for movement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decoding algorithm improves and patient capacity to interface with the machine improves as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Richard Anderson leading clinical trials at caltech.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A focus of this research is stabilizing the movements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dr. Edward Chang works on restoring the ability to communicate at UCSF using BCI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;40 characters a minute by Shenoy et al. in cursor benchmark.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turning thoughts into type which uses pattern analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chang lab uses sensors planted on the surface of the brain which have a lower resolution but a non-invasive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All BCI companies are aiming to increase bandwidth of communication signals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is still a long way to go with the technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Major limitations right now are how long the device will last, how well it will adapt to each user, and if the device will still be supported or used later on down the road.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">The brain-reading devices helping paralysed people to move, talk and touch by Liam Drew.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 23: Neuropixels 2.0: A miniaturized high-density probe for stable, long-term brain recordings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review23/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 23: Neuropixels 2.0: A miniaturized high-density probe for stable, long-term brain recordings" /><published>2022-04-16T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review23</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review23/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.10.27.358291v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Neuropixels 2.0: A miniaturized high-density probe for stable, long-term
brain recordings&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nicksteinmetz.com/#:~:text=Nick%20Steinmetz,and%20cognition%20across%20the%20brain.&quot;&gt;Nick Steinmetz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper notes for Neuropixels 2.0
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Notably, this is a pretty big collaboration. The following labs participated:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;O’Keefe Lab at UCL&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Moser Lab at NTNU&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Lee Lab at Janelia Research&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Dudman lab at Janelia Research&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hausser Lab at UCL&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Steinmetz Lab at UW&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Svoboda Lab at Janelia&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Carandini/ Harris Lab&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hantman Lab&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Haesler Lab&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels new probe :
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;has over 5000 sites, features&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;has 2 probes and a head stage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;records at 786 sites at once&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;weighs over 1 gram&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;enables recording from over &amp;gt; 10000 recording sites during free behavior in mice&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stably recording neurons over days / weeks during long terms processes like learning and memory is challenging, but important for understanding neural coding.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many attempts to record from devices that are flexible and less than $\mu$m in size.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Paper states that downside to these approaches are: make insertion difficult and do not scale at large numbers of recording sites per shank.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I don’t understand how small flexible devices could make insertion more difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More rigid and larger devices (Utah array, wire tetrodes, silicon probes) record high-quality signals for 8 weeks. However, no consistent recordings of individual neurons over the scale of months.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels: dense coverage along a line, another array: across a plane.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;algorithm stabilizes device to brain motion post hoc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;two recording channels be simultaneously recorded in the same channel with noise penalty in snr.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;At this point, I realized that there is a lot of past literature about these recording probes that I am missing. This feels like watching avengers before watching all the prequel movies.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Results
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;4 shanks, 1280 sites per shank, 5120 total sites.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;single wide band 14-bit data stream.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hardware switches can swap recording streams enabling recording from thousands of streams/experiment.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;can cover a plan of 750 x 720 $\mu$m during recording.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fig. 1
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels 2.0 is much less wide than the previous version.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Shows LFP recording and spike waveform recording (overlapping channels).&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Probe rasters and reproduced raster of dorsal striatum firing pattern across ten trials.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;7 / 8  probes recovered in working condition.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;max time recording from implant: 309 days.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fig 2.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;the proportion of spikes has a decaying distribution over the # of days after implant. A similar trend is shown in C. and D.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;hippocampus has a high proportion of firing neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;comparison of spike recording stats between labs that used the device.
                &lt;ul&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;I think this plot is hard to interpret because I know there are different conditions for each lab so plot does not necessarily show apples to apples.&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Paper claims brain motion leads to progressively less spikes during the duration of a recording.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;But they have an unsupervised learning algorithm to adjust for motion post hoc and re-detect spikes. This method increases recording stability (3E).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fig 3.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;The results from this stabilization procedure a visually very convincing.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Now they expand the timescale alignment to long intervals.
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;successful tracking across days, and weeks (figure 4). 83% tracking accuracy after 9 weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;wonder what that accuracy is across more than three months? But tracking 83% of neurons seems really good.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Average signals from two sites along a recording line and then decompose them.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fig 4
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;bank 1 and bank 2 separated to two sets of neurons and the switch helps record mapping between banks using mismatch.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;when both banks are recording noise is lower.&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;3 configurations: both banks on, bank 1 on, bank 2 on.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Neuropixels 2.0: A miniaturized high-density probe for stable, long-term brain recordings by Nick Steinmetz.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review 21: Cracking the Neural Code in Humans</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review21/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review 21: Cracking the Neural Code in Humans" /><published>2022-04-02T05:16:13-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-02T05:16:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reviews/review21</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reviews/review21/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simonsfoundation.org/2022/03/29/cracking-the-neural-code-in-humans/&quot;&gt;Cracking the Neural Code in Humans
&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simonsfoundation.org/people/emily-singer/&quot;&gt;Emily Singer&lt;/a&gt; at the Simons Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels: high resolution brain recording from implanted electrodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Until recently Neuropixel devices are only used on primates and rodents, but now they can be used in people thanks to Dr. Paulk and Dr. Cash at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cashlab.mgh.harvard.edu/people/&quot;&gt;Cashlab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neural recordings for brain computer interfaces are researched in clinical trials due to the risks associated with implantable electrodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However further development of the decoding that can be performed at various resolutions helps inform new and more effective BCI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short, fast, and simple tasks may help understand neural coding at a more basic level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Primary application is that the user would control a robotic arm or robotic device that responds to decoded brain activity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utah microelectrode array as the leading measurement device for 7 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RNN Decoder translates Neural activity from 200 neurons into characters at rate of 90 characters per minute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shenoy 2022&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your brain is actually issuing more information per second when you handwrite than when you make a straight line. That increased complexity made it easier to quickly decode the intended letter — and offers new opportunities for exploring neural coding,”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dr. Pandarinath researchers fast finger movements, unlike commonly researched reaching and grasping movements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dr. Stavisky and Dr. Shenoy are able to reliably deocde speech related neural activity from handknob area in people who can’t move their hands but can still speak.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Still the question of what machinery is used for what task is outstanding. It will be hard to map areas even between common tasks like walking and running.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lower dimension manifolds for interpreting neural recodings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuropixels code and data are public.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dr. Paulk says diversity of waveforms produced is a new and surprising result.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There still exist significant engineering challenges around neuropixels, like how to stablize the device and transmit data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>xander</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">Cracking the Neural Code in Humans by Emily Singer at the Simons Foundation.</summary></entry></feed>